Guide to the John Flesher Newsom Papers, 1909-1938 (inclusive) 1920-1926 (bulk)
Department of Special Collections
Newsom, John Flesher. Papers,
1909-1938 (inclusive)
1920-1926 (bulk)
M0747
Newsom, John Flesher.
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
These papers largely pertain to geologic and mining work in Alaska and Malaya undertaken by J.F. Newsom, with some materials pertaining to his son John Branner Newsom. Included is a field book on gold claims in Alaska and British Columbia kept by J.F. Newsom, 1915; a report by J.F. Newsom on placer gravels in Alaska, 1909; correspondence, reports, charts and tables, statements, and photographs pertaining to tin mining in Malaya, 1920-26; an undated photograph album of mining operations, possibly in Malaya; and oversize drawings of drills and a mill by J.B. Newsom, 1929-37.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from Branner Library, 1991.
Biography
John Flesher Newsom, student and associate of John Casper Branner, earned his master's and doctorate degrees in geology at Stanford University in 1892 and 1901 respectively. While engaged in his graduate studies, he also worked summers for Branner as assistant geologist on the Arkansas State Geological Survey. Newsom taught at Stanford from 1898 to 1910, when he resigned to do full time exploratory work for mining companies. He died unexpectedly in October 1928. John Branner Newsom, son of J.F. Newsom, earned his a.b. in geology at Stanford in 1922 and his engineer's degree in 1924.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
These papers largely pertain to geologic and mining work in Alaska and Mayala undertaken by John F. Newsom, with some materials pertaining to his son John Branner Newsom. Box one contains a field book on gold claims in Alaska and British Columbia kept by John F. Newsom, 1915, and a report by J.F. Newsom on placer gravels in Alaska, 1909. Box two contains correspondence, reports, charts and tables, statements, and photographs pertaining to tin mining in Malaya. The documents in folders 1 through 35 were removed from a notebook; they are the documents of "File Number One" found in the listing in folder 36. The disposition of the remaining documents on that list is unkown.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Newsom, J.B. (John Branner), 1897-; Mining--Alaska.; Mining--British Columbia.; Mining--Malaya.; Albums.; Photoprints.
Collection Contents
- Report on placer gravels, Fairbanks district, Alaska, 1909 - Parts I - IV1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Report on placer gravels, Fairbanks district, Alaska, 1909 - Part V Appendix1909 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Report on placer gravels, Fairbanks district, Alaska, 1909 - Maps (plates I, II, III)1909 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Report on placer gravels, Fairbanks district, Alaska, 1909 - Maps (plates IV, V, VI)1909 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Report on placer gravels, Fairbanks district, Alaska, 1909 - Maps (plates VII, VIII)1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Field notebook, J.F. Newsom, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Alaska, British Columbia (gold claims)
- Kampar sizing data - Data on screening tests of ores and sands from various parts of the Malay States. Jan. 29, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Data on sizing tests at Kuala Lumpur - Data on displacements and sizes of ore, clay and sands from the Malayan region. Also curves giving the results of screen tests.Feb. 10, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Data on sizes and character of bank material and dredge tails on a representative property. Also on character of tin lost and on losses in Dulong Washing. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Hindered settling ratios - Table taken from Denver Engineering Works Company.1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Free settling rates - Curves (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Screen tests on tin ore (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Comparison between Yukon Gold Screen and I.M.& M. Screens - Two letters and several tables.Feb. 4, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Classifier computations - 64 pages of computations for designing classifiers and curves setting forth the results of the computations based on actual screen analyses of ore and sands.1923 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- United Engineers Dredge Construction Program - An extract from the report of the United Engineers from "The Times of Malaya."Oct. 19, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Neill jig experiments - Letter and table from the Union Construction Company giving results or tests on Neill jigs.1921 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Value data - Charts and tables for calculating the value in the ground of tin ore with varying amounts of tin per cubic yards and varying prices for the productAug. 18, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Dredge costs and weight - Rough estimate of the cost and weight of dredges and the crew required1921 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- General principles - A statement of the problems to be met, the experiments necessary to meet them and the general method of procedure to followJune 25, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Spitz-kasten compared with double current classifier and results - A table giving comparisons of loss in jigs tailings when working a product from a Spitz-kasten classifier as compared with the double current classifier1922 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Photographs of Yukon Gold Co. dredge M-4 - Photographs of the general arrangement and the jig floor during construction1923 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Tin dredging compared with gold dredging - A statementMarch 29, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Preliminary instructions to jig operators - A statement of general principles and detailed instructions for operation of jigs and classifierApril 10, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Jig strokes and speeds - A letter to A.J. Kelman enclosing tables showing length and speed of stroke on the Kampar and Ampang dredgesFeb. 29, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Comparison between tables and jigs - An engineering cost analysisOct. 26, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Power requirements - Power required for 7-1/2 ft. dredge1923 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Cost data - Estimates of costs of jigs and classifiers compared with costs of sluices1923 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Capacity test - Letter setting forth conditions and results of capacity tests on classifier-jig systemNov. 25, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Hutch water - A statement of general principles after talking with A.W. Farhenwald by J.B.NJuly 16, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Jig feed - The ideal to be aimed for. A general statement after talking with A.W. FahrenwaldJuly 16, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Results of capacity test - A letter giving details of testNov. 23, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Capacity, cost, and weights of classifiers and jigs - Letters and detailed statement1923 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Dimensions, launder slopes, etcDec. 12, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Cost and profit estimatesJan. 1, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- General statement submitted to United Engineers - A general statement setting out the principal advantages of the classifier-jig systemFeb. 29, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Comparison of results - A series of tables giving financial comparisons between classifier-jig dredges and sluice dredgesJan. 15, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Construction of Cooley jig - working drawings for a steel jig. (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Letters to Malayan tin enclosing drawings - General letters specific about sluice gradesFeb. 11, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Photographs of samples - 12 photographs illustrating graphically the results to be expected from jigs working on a classified product1924 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Sketch of packed jig bed - A sketch illustrating the losses in a jig bed which has been allowed to pack and setting forth the methods of keeping the bed freeAug. 6, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Conditions of testNov. 25. 1923 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- List of documents taken to Singapore by J.B. NewsomAug. 14, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Photos (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Assorted charts, tables, graphs (Box 2, Folder 38)
- J.F. Newsom - Memos regarding Kuala-Lumpur mining1921-22 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Articles1923, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Album of photographs of mining operations, possibly in Malaya (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Published article on tin, with some photographs taken by J.B. Newsom (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Drawings: (Box 3, Folder 3)
  sketch of opening for 3'6" mine shaft drill, 1937 -- Mill D, Bloomington Limestone Company, 1929; designed by J.B. Newsom -- Plat of lands owned by Wm. H. and John F. Newsom, Bartholomew County, IN, 1921 -- Five foot shaft drill, designed by J. B. Newsom, 1934